software engineering radio episode 46
refactoring part 1
[Music]
in today's episode I'm going to talk
with Martin Lippert so Martin do you
want to say some words about yourself
hello Ava thank you for being on the
show so my name is Martin Lippert and
I'm working as a consultant coach for IT
agile it's a small consulting company in
in Germany in Hamburg and my main focus
is working on on agile methods on one
side so I'm helping teams to become
agile to adopt agile methods to stay
agile and to improve their the
development process and on the other
side I'm working on an agile
technologies or technologies that are
somehow related to edge and methods so
I'm deeply involved somehow and this
kind of Eclipse technology and I'm
interested in spraying and stuff like
that and how to combine all these
technologies so and one of my favorite
technologies and that's related to to
agile methods of course refactoring and
that's that that's why I'm here today
okay so today we are going to talk about
our refactoring so first of all the
question is what does refactoring
actually mean so refactoring means
improving the internal structure the
internal design of a software system
without changing the external behavior
so that that basically means to to
improve the design to to restructure the
software and without adding features
without removing features without
without changing the real real behavior
you can discuss a lot what what the
behavior means if it needs a the
performance or it includes just the UI
or the API or whatever it depends on the
context of your software but it
basically means improving the internal
structure to maintain and to cheaply and
modify the software in the future to
keep it healthy and to to keep it soft
okay so where does that term come from
who coined it uhm the term originals in
and the I think in a workshop paper
there was
published at Uppsala conference in the
early 90s and I think mainly William
Updike he wrote a PhD thesis about
refactoring object on it systems for
Roth Johnson at the University of Obama
Obama Illinois I think other was in 1993
I think and and he let's say he
researched all the the basic ideas
behind what is refactoring and how does
refactoring works and how some factoring
different from from just changing a
piece of software the next breakthrough
was um was done by John Roberts and John
Brent and they built they built the
refactoring tool support they will the
real first refactoring browser
refactoring tool and for small talk and
I think that was at that point in time
was more songs on silent about this
around this kind of of refactoring ideas
and the real that's a worldwide
breakthrough or or real real main
interest in the term refactoring in the
the late 90s through the book by Martin
Fowler about refactoring and with the
movement of these agile methods where
refactoring is a main part of so why did
Martin write that book I mean at that
specific time even though the idea was
are already quite old um I think the the
idea became much more important in this
area of agile methods because in agile
methods you typically ever you start
with a very very small implementation
small system and you basically working
all the time improving an existing piece
of software and the idea of incremental
design and and and creating the
architecture of the system over time
basically means that you need to improve
your the structure of your existing
system all the time or every day all the
time you work on on this on the software
and I think therefore it was really
important to have some some kind of
guidance some kind of
to support and then maybe maybe a good
book like like the Belmont and Fowler to
give you some some hints and tips and
tricks and and and some provide some
nuts and bolts or what to do and what
don't to do and the book is real is it's
a real I think it's a real brilliant
book and everybody should read it and
even if you do not do agile or extreme
programming or whatever it's just some
some fundamental know-how how to work
with operating systems and in the book I
think him he the the big true parts are
on the one hand he tells you a lot about
what are the smelly smelly points in the
system what he calls a cold smell so
what it was an ugly design what what are
the typical pieces of code where you
should change the internal design into
eternal structure and on the other hand
he gives you a lot of advice and a lot
of patterns and what or how you can
improve internal structure internal
design so it gives you a lot of guidance
how to let's say how to rename a method
how can you rename a meth it's a very
very sounds like a very very simple
factoring but if you do not do not have
to support you can think a lot of if you
have a huge system with thousands of
dependencies on one particular method
you can think a lot of how to
step-by-step implement this kind of
effect ring without breaking system for
a long time so the whole idea is based
on doing small changes testing small
changes all the time to to keep you
happy and safe that you do not introduce
new box while you're factoring so the
software one of the first things
obviously for refactoring is to know
when to apply them so you were talking
about coats melts and how do you
actually find them I not everybody can
can sniff the software so just say right
yeah that's right that's right I think
sometimes you just need a good
experience and good know-how from a
phone from several systems you've built
in the past and on the other hand in the
or that many cults meds described and
there they exist some tools to which try
to identify cult smells try to sniff
whole smells and some tools like maybe
find box this is very simple tool but
it's it's a very very fine granular
level more sophisticated tool they try
to analyze structures dependencies
between classes dependencies between
packages and sizes of methods for
example and they can tell you for
example well yeah you have a class
that's contains methods it's quite long
and maybe you should think about them
extract method or split it into
different methods so there there's some
tools I think so is it rather something
that that you can say there is is it
hard scientific things to say this is a
code smell or not or is it rather
something that comes out of experience
and and more like soft know-how
I think it is more it's more a question
of soft know how I learn any experience
it's more like you you have to implement
a new feature for a piece of software
and you take a look at the structure and
you find out that the structure is
simply does not work for for a new
feature or it's quite complicated or you
think or you find in the in the code
many different pieces you need to change
to implement a new feature and I think
that you you have a good feeling about
what part of the of the structure is not
good and does not fit into this new
feature and I think then based on this
experience and in this just reading code
you can identify a lot of these cold
smelts just yourself without any any
kind of tools okay so how does that feed
into daily work how do you do
refactoring is I mean some of the
projects that I know say you do a period
of refactoring after delivering a
release for example so so it's that a
valid approach or how do you do that and
my point of view is that that
refactoring belongs to your daily
programming work so if you if you
implement a software it's just like
creating a new class
is refactoring all the time so I I I'm
I'm refactoring my project on my piece
of code all the time I rename methods I
split methods I extract code I rename
classes all the time to keep the the
design healthy all the time because if
you if you think about I just I just put
this piece into the software and doesn't
matter if it is if it's a clay or not
it's melts or not doesn't matter after
the next release we have a plenty of
time to to improve the structure my
experience is that you will never get
the time to to improve the structure and
even if you get that time it's it's much
more complicated to the refactoring
after you have implemented for several
weeks a month features then if you do
the refactoring all the time so it's
really it's a thing it's fun for me it's
maybe you can say it's more important
than programming ok so what you're
saying is such a period of organized
refactoring is not something that you
should do then in the the next question
yes how do you may actually make people
refactor because obviously this is what
what you're saying is it's something
that every program is is supposed to do
as an ongoing task yes and they're much
like history of development for example
there are a lot of programmers that will
probe most likely not do it so yeah how
do you deal with that problem well I
think it's a different problem because
it's I think somewhat belongs to every
developer to do refactoring all the time
and it's it's let's get hard if it gets
hard if you have a team where five
people do refactoring all the time and
then belongs to their daily work just
from a natural point of view and and
some people don't so it's it's it's
quite hard to convince them that the
factoring is good so maybe you can you
can dupe a programming with them and
then try to give them a try too
maybe not to teach them refactoring but
but to to give them an impression how if
during really works and that that
refactoring is if you do it only day and
the daily basis it's really it's an easy
task and so it's not a complicated stuff
it's it's really with a tool support you
have today in the modern IDs it's really
easy to refactor it it's it's more it's
easier than creating a new class maybe
so it's really easy everybody should do
but if someone is convinced that your
factoring is not necessary at all and
it's just you bear them useless work so
maybe it's hard to to convince those
people just from these these theoretical
points of view okay but I think it's
it's just a few of you if you want to
create a software that's healthy over
time refactoring is you cannot do it
without refactoring yeah that's
certainly true now we have already I
mean I already mentioned testers and
development so what what is the
relationship between refactoring and
history of development I think the
relation between test-driven development
and refactoring think about it um I
think test-driven development is a
development approach to do Tetra
development and here you create a test
class and then you implement the code
and because of refactoring mainly
belongs to implementing the code on the
on the one side it's just you you Friday
says case and you implement the code and
think oh I need to reflect through some
stuff and then you do you check with the
stuff and you make the code the test
green so that's one aspect another
aspect is that a refactoring if you do
not have real safe to support and you do
manual refactoring stuff and you really
need a test field and a test case to to
be sure that you do not change the
behavior you do not introduce box and
stuff like that so
refactoring without tool support and
without a good test suite is is like is
like doing some crazy stuff without a
safety net so you really need the test
case and safety and that's that's the
second level and the third level I think
is
what what some people say um that you
need to refactor your test cases as well
not just the cold but you can also think
of coats melts and test cases so many
similar test methods or huge setups or
whatever we need to refactor a test
cases as well yeah because you need to
have the same quality in in the test
cases as in in the real code okay what
do i I mean um so basically what you're
saying is if I if I don't have any test
cases and I have that quality of code
I'm basically screwed because I can't do
anything so and I will have this bad
quality forever so what do I do in that
situation I think I think the real
challenge then is to to write test cases
for that code and then refactor the code
but it's not always that easy as it
sounds like because some in most cases
if you do not have test cases it's
really really hard and really
complicated to introduce test cases for
for some classes that are written
without a unit tests in mind and they're
not really testable you cannot whatever
inject dependencies or whatever so you
really need to to maybe somehow get it a
first step into that class to make it
testable and then write a piece of test
code and then maybe change another small
piece or the class to make it even more
testable and then write some some more
tests and if you have a good solid test
case or test suite for that class you
can you can do the real refactoring work
but of course these these small change
at the beginning it was also refactoring
okay so um I think there is a book about
that working efficiently with the legacy
code yes written by Micheal feathers and
it's it's titled yes I'm working
effectively with legacy code that's a
real real nice book he describes a lot
of techniques how to implement those
tests and whatever techniques you can
apply to implement those tests like a
smoke
tests and stuff like that it's a real
it's a nice book okay talking about
books we already mentioned the Fowler
book so and that I think gives a
collection of refactoring patterns so
why should I read it I mean what what's
the benefit of reading through that I
think that the benefit is that you first
of all get an idea about typical Cole
smells okay that's that's one one factor
and another aspect is that you get a
real real great impression how to
step-by-step refactor a piece of code
for in a specific situation and it
provides a lot of stuff like how do you
can step by step you name a method or
how I can split a hierarchy or I can
change inheritance hierarchies and I can
change relationships between classes and
stuff like that and it's a real it's
it's maybe maybe not a book which you
need to read from the first to the last
let's page once but it's it's really
worth to read all these patterns and all
these these refactoring guidance that's
provided in the book to get a feeling
how I can change the internal structure
without changing the behavior and how I
can can move forward in small steps
makes me wonder whether there are any
other refactorings patterns or books
that I should read or three guns to
refactoring um yeah they're there they
exist some some some books from some
more books those of them Martin Fowler
book is it's the refactoring book of
course and there's refactoring workbook
written by William Wake it's more some
kind of practical guidance how to learn
refactoring and have to do some
practical examples and stuff like that
it's it's also a nice book and if you
take a look at those those two books
they're both and basically the the book
by Matt Lauer they're both on these
these bays level of refactoring they're
working on on on the class level on the
relationship level between single
classes and all these object oriented
concepts
like inheritance or relationships and
stuff like that they're not working on
on higher levels I think their their
session system the two maybe two
refactoring parents that are focused on
more more high level refactorings like
separating presentation from from domain
but it's really it remains a vague and
in in the book the guidance and the
examples so they're the next step I
think is the book by written by Joshua
curious key about refactoring to
patterns but he analyzed at what are
typical situations and typical cold
smells where for example should they
should introduce an observer pattern how
you can can introduce or extract a
visitor pattern from from from from your
code or or other patterns a lot of
patterns in that book and how you can
refactor two patterns so typical Gotham
errands I think and on the other side M
the the opposite reactions as well so
how I can remove an unnecessary
implement a pattern from your goal where
it's not not really necessary what makes
it cook more more complicated than it
needs to be yeah I actually believe that
every factory every fraction can be done
in in both ways so yes so to say forward
and backward yeah yeah okay so you can
extract a method you can inline a have
it and both both worth so it's not
really extract Methodist it's the
battery factoring an inline method maybe
if it seems seem self but it's really
it's really worth to get them getting
depression of both sides okay you have
already mentioned some tools like the
original Smalltalk refactoring browser
and so which church should I be aware
off and which should I use
I think the today the modern the current
IDE implementations like like Eclipse
for Java or idea for Java whatever some
some a lot of tools I do want to
advertise some tools here but all these
modern ideas they they all implement
refactoring support on the base level so
you can can
you can rename a class can do all these
renaming class methods whatever and you
can can do movements and and most of
them provide even advanced refactoring
support and on the on the real on the
level of single keystrokes can just
rename a class with a single keystroke
and extract a local variable with a
single keystroke as really its need to
have it some summer in your blood and in
your fingers to have all these these
keystrokes available all the time to do
the perfecting all the time and this
refactoring suppose really it's it's
great I don't want to work without such
a refactoring support I'm in such ITES
because it's really AM it's really great
support what it was important on the one
hand is that those that there exists two
different kinds of refactoring supports
or affection support in such tools on
the one hand you have to support that
really is is safe you can you can
believe the IDE that it takes care of
changing all the references to your
named class I'm changing all these
whatever that you do not change the
behavior of your existing system and it
can be safe it's it's it really does not
change the behavior and it takes care of
that it ensures you for you that and on
the other side there are some
reflections are more advanced more
complicated and more general maybe like
a change method signature or even
extract method and in some situations is
quite difficult in Java to implement
where the IDE cannot give you the give
you the safety of that the behavior is
not changed so it's somehow it's great
we have all these ID support cosmics
easy to it makes it easy to factor and
that's all the references and stuff like
that but it does not give you the
possibility to skip your your safety net
to skip the test cases you can always
need the test cases
even if you have great to support by the
IDE so but but there are other like
specialized refactoring tools outside of
typical IDs because so far you've only
talked about what what the the IDS would
support I think that there exists some
some folks have for eclipses because six
some plugins but provided there's no
traction support and I think for for the
visual studio world they exist some some
some plugins and some some additions
that provide factory support for that
I'm not aware of special other tools
that gives you some some provides it
some help or some support okay so
basically I I should use the ID and and
that's it I think so
one thing that I found quite artists
today people talk about a lot a lot
about Java and beer being statically
typed and the advantage of Java offering
more support for these because you can
reason about the type and therefore have
better possibilities for a complication
for example or even refactoring yeah
even though I mean the the original
refactoring browser that we've talked
about a was for small talks for friend
and I mean really type language so how
does that fit together even though
refactoring appears to be something that
is really good really well supported by
statically typed languages only it is a
concept that was introduced by
dynamically typed languages mm-hm
um I think the the the main reason is
that that most of the research was done
in in in the early nineties in these
update or in the world in the Smalltalk
area gives you a lot of possibilities of
of implementing stuff into the IDE and
and stuff like that so was the research
stuff for that for that and the
refactoring support there was built into
this module refactoring browser was was
really grateful for that point in time
and but if you take a look at that
so actually compared to the statically
typed languages it's it's really
complicated to do our renamed class or a
name method in small talk and finding
out where is this method called and
where it's not called where's another
method meant um and they sometimes they
just say okay I just rename every method
and system that it's called whatever and
to whatever new without analyzing if
it's really the same method or it's it's
an invocation of the same method or
completely different method because it
cannot know which method was meant
because it kind of cannot analyze a
steadily static typing of its system so
it's it's a lot easier to implement this
is automatics refactoring support for
steadily typed languages and it's much
more complicated to do it for it for
dynamic languages I can't believe that
there there might might appear some some
refactoring support tools for for
dynamically typed languages but it's a
lot more difficult to implement and to
realize um interestingly um people were
working on for example Ubu in Ruby on
Rails project they told me that and
they're really big fans of refactoring
they told me that they have looked they
do not need to refactor so much in the
dynamic diamond ammok language world
like they do typically of I need in
these steadily tapping which is I do not
know why and then they cannot like if I
could not explain it to me why they do
not need time factors so much in the
dynamic world but it was just an
observation or maybe just a feeling and
I found it quite interesting I have no
experience myself with these ten and you
typed stuff so I cannot really prove it
or explain why why where that this
feeling comes from but it was an
interesting observation I think or maybe
if you don't have such a good idea
support you do it less regularly but I
mean who knows I I read some some
reports that said that there is there is
a risk of refactoring yourself to death
so to say so that you just do
refactoring all the time and you do much
more refactoring
you do actually implementation work is
instead a common problem or I mean isn't
it
naive to to assume that you can just
hack away and then refactoring will take
care of all the active stuff that you're
doing and that will still be an
efficient process of implementation I
think you need a good balance between
programming and refactoring I think and
I know many people sometimes I belong to
this group now I think I can I can I can
improve this more and I can I can
improve in more and more and more and it
gets beautiful and more beautiful and
more beautiful code and and I love this
piece of code and makes it more even
more better and and whatever and I think
you need it's it's just somehow you
spend a lot of time doing this stuff
without really without really improving
the internal structure without getting
some some kind of benefit out of it I
think you need a good balance between
these two forces of implementing stuff
or adding features and refactoring and I
think the the main goal or the the main
the main motivation for me is to keep a
software soft and healthy not to keep it
over healthy or over soft or completely
flexible for everything just being
pragmatic and say what what are the
current features I need to implement for
us for this piece of software and what
is a good structure for that and if I
implement a feature and think after
implementing the future how does the
design looks like and I think our cases
it's melts somehow and I improve it but
I just improve it until it does not
smell so just do not approve it to the
to the ideal best design ever known or
whatever okay so I if should if you take
an economic perspective it's basically
an investment into the future so you're
saying okay I have this piece of code it
has bad design and I assume that by
improving the design who
have a higher productivity in the future
and the how do you judge whether this
refactoring will pay off as an
investment and here will not be
something that is just good beautifying
yeah I think I think really judging or
or marinated in money somehow it's it's
quite difficult because it's it's a unit
who can who can really measure how how
maintainable the piece of suffers or how
how much is a cousin in in five years to
add new features I think it really pays
off quickly if you have a healthy
software system healthy design and and
if you factor all the time because um it
doesn't matter if if you implement the
feature today or in five years into such
a piece of software it always costs the
same does not cause okay if you if we
implement it well if you think about
this feature now it's it's cheap to
integrate into the system and if you
think about it tomorrow it costs a lot
of money because we need to change a lot
of code and we need to refactor the
basic basic architecture of the system
or whatever so I think it's more this is
kind of idea if you if you are going to
implement a piece of software that lives
for for a longer period of time maybe
four month or four four years or maybe
four it does not here's
I think it's an inherit goal of keeping
this piece of software healthy and I
think the only way to keep this piece of
self a healthy is to to refactoring from
the first day on all the time so it you
cannot you cannot for my point of view
can I live without it
I am on the other hand I'm pretty sure
that there exist projects where you just
implement let's say one way software or
throw way suffer yes that's what you
think you're doing maybe and now I know
of situations where this is this is
really true because I enough of people
they implement software for brokers
and then those brokers they really need
a software for tomorrow and just for
tomorrow and just for this specific
contract or for the specific market
situation or whatever and they needed
really a highly specified piece of
software just for for this deal okay so
they they program the software and
doesn't matter if they do copy and paste
or whatever they just needed for one day
and they throw it away after the day so
and then they need it may be another
piece of software next day okay so what
you're saying is basically that it's a
technique that I'm using on a more
fine-grained level and also it is
something that you somehow need to judge
when to do by your experience so what
I'm wondering is should a manager or a
project leader care about refactoring or
is there anything from the management
level that that you can do with regards
to refactoring to enforce it or is it
just some fine grained stuff that a good
developer does I think the the goal from
the management point of view is to take
care of a good design in your software
and because you would like to have a
piece of software that is maintainable
and changeable in the future that is
your management goal you would like to
have a piece of software that in two
years you can you can add features with
the same speed and the same quality as
you do now so maybe maybe it's involved
for the management but I think it's it's
often a goal for to manage from the
management point of view and maybe it
doesn't matter how the team realizes
this goal or how the team ensures that
that the adding this feature whatever
features needs or whatever changes in
requirements they may make her in the
future
can be implemented fast and quickly and
a high quality level into the software
maybe it doesn't matter how the team
ensures that it can that lets be able in
the future to do this but I think that
refactoring is the most important
technique for the for the for the team
to ensure this goal so it's not really
I think refactoring as it technique
itself maybe does not matter to the
management so much it's more the the
effects that you create with refactoring
and that matters to the management it's
there some some advice that you could
give to a project manager and whether
the when he should bring in someone that
looks at this year that that improves
the refactoring techniques in the team
so is there some kind of of of hint that
that hints manager okay so obviously the
team is not doing refactoring in a in a
proper way
and for that reason we now have quality
problems and unusual find a way of
improving the refactoring knowledge in
my team I think I think of course
getting people into the team that are
experienced on refactoring that they can
teach other people or like they can show
other people how to refactor and how to
improve that that design Isis is always
useful and we have consultant over
whatever for for a limited period of
time inside the project that is
experience with this kind of techniques
but I think I think for many teams that
I know or where I was involved in it's
difficult to say okay here's a book I
read this book it's good sounds good and
just do it from from the management
because all the develops things okay
he's he's a manager he does not know
what really happens here inside the code
or inside through the system oh let him
tell everything and we will throw it
away just a book put into the Reverend
on the back on the board yeah okay so
thanks a lot for for talking about
refactorings we will have another
episode that is going to be going to
talk about big refactorings
with martin as well so and stay tuned
for more information about refactoring
in the next episodes
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Pauley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineer a do
website for details